I compounded every science-based tools and techniques that angry Huberman talks about in his podcast and
made a simple routine I follow the routine for fourteen days and give you some insights
on my experience at the end of this video I'll also guide you on a freak
notion them played on which you can edit and structure your routine back by neuroscience to
optimize your day and you Huberman is a neuroscientist and an associate professor from Stanford university
you create some awesome podcast about productivity look mean maximize them are true parental at lyricism
and very useful self or corning had been watched a lot of his videos on Europe
and made notes for later use after reviewing all the things he mentioned and doing a
little bit of research on my own end I decided I would follow everything that Andrew
habermann suggests the neurologically write to him to follow to get all the cognitive benefits without
using any supplements in simple words brain hacking without nootropics
before we move forward I would like to undress that each and every action of this
routine is based on handy hooperman podcast and has a scientific reason for it science based
tools for everyday life
and for the sake of simplicity have compounded the routine into three major categories those are
morning phase one and face to
so let's start with the morning
so I just woke up right now that time is five forty am it's really dark
outside so let's turn on the lights and now I'm gonna go and write down my
wake up then I study
the reason for writing down the wake up time every day is to figure out the
temperature minimum of our body most of the time is just to us before our average
pickup time this will help us to pick a specific time to do hard mental work
in the day more on that in a while
it's weird to drink salt orderly in the morning it's not taste the end little
whatever
it is veered to drink salt water early in the morning but neurons transfers signals Canadians
from one into other through ionic conduction sodium is the main salt which helps the flow
of tions so adding some salt in a glass of water helps all neurons to wake
up and function properly early in the morning
usually I like to bring some black coffee the moment I wake up but Andrew says
having caffeine only in the morning can lead to an energy dip during afternoon also called
the afternoon crash and we may feel for the and tired therefore craving more caffeine more
coffee
caffeine is best after ninety to one twenty minutes of waking up so yeah I'm going
to refrain from that and meanwhile do some meditation and listen to an audio look the
more a person asks questions practices figuring out answers and trains their ability to think the
better they will actually be able to think all right so it's past ninety minutes and
I can't resist Catherine anymore so I'm gonna bring some coffee and get ready for some
self generated forward ambulation
I'll tell you what that means
cells generated forward ambulation it's just a fancy turn to say I'm gonna go for a
walk or maybe run
when we move our body it generates I moved and causes optical flow which is good
for the nervous system and it activates many parts of our brain meanwhile lowering the functions
of amygdala to build better entrance he suggests to take him to in his with short
bursts and then following that with a long exhale so when you're at a steady cadence
and you're feeling good do double inhales
while you're running double inhale exhale double inhale exhale is a terrific way to breathe while
you're an ongoing effort apart from activating various parts of our brain and building endearments it's
also important to see sunlight early in the morning to signal the neurons that its data
and it's time for us to be more alert then the neuron said a huge domino
effect on all of our body organs
all right so we are done with are running and after this I'm gonna go to
the gym this may be a lot of physical activity for me but you know I
follow David Gauguin's I'd like to stay on drew the hydration Killick your mother eclipse your
legs are all sewer if I guess since places stress fractures no you don't you got
sore fucking legs get on your head they are speaking of David gorgons I'm currently following
this us navy seal work out which I'm gonna make a video little this video is
all about Andy Huberman so let's get this work out done and I'll meet you and
I'm back from the gym
all right some back from the gym and now I'm gonna take a cold shower really
good and then start my work from around ten or so let's go
cold water treatment could increase our dopamine level in a healthy and natural
while I take a shower let me tell you about the linear face this phase of
the day is for repetitive and analytical tasks this phase will pay more attention to the
mind by following good practices based on a treaty and rhythm of the day basically all
radion rhythm is to work for nine minutes and rest for twenty minutes work for ninety
minutes to rest for twenty minutes it will help us to do many sessions of fulcra
deep work without feeling exhausted
these days everyone is doing intermittent fasting for weight loss and burning more fat but and
you puts emphasis on how fasting could increase our epinephrine and dopamine levels and focus more
on our work apart from burning tremendous amounts of fats fasting could increase our focus and
attention by increasing adrenaline epinephrine is made by the dopamine molecule the more the dopamine molecule
works the more motivated and driven we are towards doing a certain task the rays of
dopamine and epinephrine all together increases focus attention motivation and gives us the driving energy to
work for are
so this is the part where the temperature minimum comes to played the best time to
do deep work is after four to six hours of my temperature minimum so if I
wake up at five thirty am my temperature minimum would be free three him and the
best time for me to do some deep work would be
after nine thirty is so right now it's ten him and let's start our the accession
our body's internal temperature rises from the time be baker so what we're trying to do
is sketch that steep temperature rise and optimize are ninety minutes of deep work in a
way this will allow us to do the most mentally challenging and intense world early in
the day and also and you suggest to get into ultra deep work by turning on
airplane mode avoiding all kinds of distractions and listen to some low level white noise while
world to increase our focus and concentration
white noise has been shown to really enhance brain states for learning actually can have a
detrimental effect on auditory learning and maybe even the development of the auditory system in very
young children in particular in infants he also talks about bunch of other beets and noises
but it really comes down to personal preference and for me I like to switch bitten
binaural beets and white noise depending on the mood and type of work I'm getting into
all right so we are done with her ninety minutes of deep world and I'm a
bit hungry right now but I'm not gonna eat tell to pm because I'm fasting and
that must be my order hold on a sec
for look what I got here
get a bomb at a bar
to boost fastings effects even more and you suggest to drink by Mary it's a special
Kennedy grown in Argentina and has more caffeine than regularly it could increase focus and post
fat burning
all right so I made some year by Mary and don't ask me how I made
it because
so the reason behind that nervous laughter is because yerba matter is not made like this
traditionally it's made in a part and its consumed through a metallic straw while pulling sips
of water over but you know it's my first day I'm learning
so the next thing in phase one is to learn something so I listen to an
Audi book for about thirty to forty minutes and while I listened to the holy book
I look outside the window and put in that I'm a main character in a movie
where the main character is learning something that will drastically change his life
yeah that's about right but all jokes aside when we try to multitask we are not
getting any real benefit from any of the activities so it's important to not do any
mental tasks while listening to an audio book so that our focus is an diverted and
we could concentrate more on listening and believe it or not but looking outside the window
while listening to audiobook has helped me to become more present and retain more information from
the audiobook
all right so it's time for lunch and and so angry right now I'm so relieved
to see food I'm having a protein shake some chicken breasts salad and some brown rice
keeping it on the lord side because they can in starch and then and starchy foods
make us feel sleepy however carbs are still needed for recovery from workout and physical exertion
so adding some amounts as useful as long as it doesn't make us feel the Tajik
so regardless of having less cob's in my lunch I still feel kind of sleepy so
yeah I'm gonna take a quick nap right now and then talk to you after thirty
to forty minutes good night but and you got a better solution than just maps and
that is to do in SDR enis de stands for non sleep depressed it is a
technique of giving our body proper rest without actually sleeping it works by listening to a
guided meditation and focusing on their voice and following each and every step
that was great it was like my body is hypnotized and I don't want to move
my arms or legs and in the video ends I feel so refreshed right now and
SDR
I'm gonna do in star from now I suggest you try and SDR yourself whenever you
want to take a nap
from here starts face to okay the nonlinear face the face when we are the most
creative throughout the day nonlinear face starts after seven to nine hours of taken up is
the best time to get into creative world and brainstorm ideas
all right so it's three pm right now and like earlier I'm gonna turn on airplane
mode on my phone and add to debug sessions for this time one will be from
three pm to four thirty pm and I'll take thirty minutes of rest and then I'll
start the second one which will be from five pm to six thirty be after six
thirty pm we'll head out to see some light and I'll tell you how that will
help us to have better sleep and follow the circadian rhythm of the day so let's
turn on some white noise in the background and get to work
this video has been interrupted by me if you're enjoying the konen so far then I
would really really appreciate you if you hit the light button as your like is very
valuable to me and this channel is all about learning new things and sharing the experience
with visual storytelling so if you're interested in that subscribe to my channel for more or
some going in like this all right back to face to
as I've been sitting around for the whole day going out will help me to feed
my brain with some variety you feel my energy simply with the mood also if I
could manage to meet up with my friends will increase my energy as social connections increase
baseline dopamine by a large factor another reason for going out and seeing some evening light
is because it's a line with the circadian cycle of the day it's a cycle that
repeats every twenty four hours and is dependent on the surrounding of an organism light and
dark are the two major factors that affect the circadian cycle we sleep wake up it
feel tired and do everything based on the circadian rhythm of the day so if we
figure out circadian rhythm and make it work for us then we had a sleep cycle
therefore it was important aspect to wake up and do forward ambulation so that our brain
reacts to light and activates all parts of our brain and body and at the evening
I'm seeing the sun setting following with darkness it will be easier for me to transition
tonight mode and fall asleep better and with that being said we were moving on to
our final lap
so it's the final phase now and that is to follow good practices for better sleep
I don't pay much attention to my sleep I often sleep for six hours and you
can clearly see that by my dark circles
so let's follow good practices for sleeping and have a good night's sleep number one elevating
your feet with a pillow number two keeping the room dark and chill so let's turn
on the air conditioner number three is wearing an eye mask if you cannot keep the
room dark so it will not be needed here number for taking a hot shower before
bed I'll not be doing this because today I'm already feeling sleepy I'll try this on
other days and number five is to inhale and exhale deeply while on with that sounded
wrong but carrying forward finally he talks about how important it is to breed from your
nose while you're sleeping he recommends to apply some medicinal tape and it can also prevent
snoring not that I snore I just want to breathe from my nose that's
so I've completed fourteen days of following andry humans routine and honestly I just feel great
like no kidding these past few days have been so much fun and I feel a
lot energetic than my usual sense the year by Mary is doing stuff to me and
I didn't even prepare it the traditional way I'm thinking of buying a Marty and prepare
it in the right way like the Argentineans do and get high with no but seriously
I'm enjoying my year by Mary I'm enjoying my fasting I don't feel much hungry nowadays
which is super good if you want to lose weight and maintain a healthy lifestyle and
avoid all junk food and stuff and sometimes I even forget to eat lunch like it's
three pm and then I remember
a ship I have to eat lunch now let's talk about the work aspect like listening
to white music and manorial beats while working it has helped me a lot to focus
on one thing and do the hard mental work early in the day I'm not like
one of those guys who could study for six to era straight I'm like let's study
then chill then let's still more so for me blocking my time into ninety minutes of
work and twenty minutes of rest and following that throughout the day has helped me a
lot so these past few days have been amazing I feel really an elder day but
at the same instant fourteen days is very less amount of time to conclude anything but
you know I still like it I really like how Andy your bermans takes complex subjects
and make it really easy to understand for us common people who are not so wise
in the ways of science so as promised have attached the link to the routine and
it's completely free you just have to make a account on notion if you don't have
one for each major section of the routine have attached links to and you bermans podcast
and research that bad the performed action
and finally I want to say if you're someone who listens to Andrew Huberman podcast and
interested in self development maximizing productivity and stuff then I think you should consider subscribing to
my channel also what's this video to see my spartan journey which is ongoing right now
and I'm going to share some insights after it's done another reason to subscribe